<document name="Keykit Special Variables" title="Special Variables" >
<blanklink/>
Below are descriptions of the global variables that have special
meanings within KeyKit.  Most of these
are built-in to KeyKit, but some are implemented with code in the
user-defined library.
<blankline/>
<list>
<listitem name="Abortonerr" bold="yes" />
When set to 1, KeyKit will abort when an error occurs.  The default is 0.
<listitem name="Abortonint" bold="yes" />
When set to 1, KeyKit will abort when an interrupt is received.  The default is 1.
<listitem name="Arraysort" bold="yes" />
When set to 1, the index values in
the "for ( i in arr )" statement will be processed in sorted order.
The default is 0, so that the order of index values is not sorted.
<listitem name="Autoresize" bold="yes" />
When set to 1, resizing the main KeyKit window will result in the
proportionate resizing of all the individual tool windows.
Default is 0, so that making the main window bigger will get
you more space for new tools rather than just making the existing
tools bigger.
<listitem name="Clicks" bold="yes" />
The number of clicks per beat.  Default is 96.
<listitem name="Clicksperclock" bold="yes" />
When <font face="Courier">Sync!=0</font>, this is the number of KeyKit clicks per MIDI clock.
Default is 1.
<listitem name="Clocksperclick" bold="yes" />
When <font face="Courier">Sync!=0</font>, this is the number of MIDI clocks per KeyKit click.
Default is 1.  To avoid confusion when adjusting
<font face="Courier">Clicksperclock</font> and <font face="Courier">Clocksperclick</font>,
you should ensure that at least one of those two variables
has a value of 1.
<listitem name="Consolefifo" bold="yes" />
The automatically-opened fifo that can be used
to read characters from the console.
<listitem name="Current" bold="yes" />
This phrase contains all currently-depressed notes.
<listitem name="Defpriority" bold="yes" />
This is the default priority of new tasks (though normally,
tasks inherit the priority of the task that spawns them).
<listitem name="Dirseparator" bold="yes" />
This string is the machine-dependent value that separates directory
entries within a pathname.  For example, on Unix, it is "/".
<listitem name="Dragquant" bold="yes" />
This number is used to quantize the dragging of notes with the Group tool.
<listitem name="Eof" bold="yes" />
This value is returned when you do a <font face="Courier">get()</font> on a closed (or nonexistent)
fifo.
<listitem name="Errorfunc" bold="yes" />
The function specified by this pointer is automatically called when
a non-fatal execution error occurs.
<listitem name="Filter" bold="yes" />
The value of this variable is a collection of bitflags that
determines what MIDI messages are filtered out of received MIDI input.
Macros for the bit values that can be set in the value of Filter
are: CHANPRESSURE, CONTROLLER, PROGRAM, PRESSURE, PITCHBEND, SYSEX,
POSITION, SONG, STARTSTOPCONT, and CLOCK.
Default value is 0, i.e. nothing is filtered.
<listitem name="Keypath" bold="yes" />
This string is the list of directories in which to search for
KeyKit function libraries.  Default is machine-dependent, usually computed
on the fly by the executable, though you can override it by defining a
KEYPATH environment variable.  Note: if you change Keypath after KeyKit has
started executing, you need to call the <font face="Courier">rekeylib()</font> function in order
to rescan all the directories for their keylib.k files - otherwise the
change will be ineffective.
<listitem name="Loadverbose" bold="yes" />
If non-zero, the dynamic loading of each KeyKit function is announced.
Default is 0.
<listitem name="Lowcore" bold="yes" />
When the amount of free memory falls below this number, warnings begin to be
issued to encourage exiting.  Default is 50000.
<listitem name="Machine" bold="yes" />
This string holds the machine type (e.g. "win", "unix", "amiga").
<listitem name="Maxatonce" bold="yes" />
This controls how many simultaneously-depressed notes can be handled
on MIDI input.  Default value is 256.
<listitem name="Merge" bold="yes" />
If non-zero, MIDI input is merged into MIDI output.  Default is 1.
<listitem name="Mergefilter" bold="yes" />
If non-zero (and if Merge is non-zero), this value is a bitmask used
to determine which channels are <b>not</b> merged from MIDI input to MIDI output.
For example, if the value of Mergefilter is <font face="Courier">41&lt;&lt;4</font>, then channel
5 will not be merged.  Any number of bits in Mergefilter can be set.
<listitem name="Mfformat" bold="yes" />
The value of this variable is the type (0,1,2) of the last MIDI file read
with <font face="Courier">midifile()</font>.
<listitem name="Midififo" bold="yes" />
The automatically-opened fifo that can be used
to read notes from MIDI input.
<listitem name="Mousefifo" bold="yes" />
The automatically-opened fifo that can be used
to read events from the mouse.  The items read from this fifo are
arrays - the index values are <font face="Courier">"button"</font>, <font face="Courier">"x"</font>, and <font face="Courier">"y"</font>.
<listitem name="Now" bold="yes" />
The current time, in clicks.
<listitem name="Offsetfilter" bold="yes" />
If non-zero (and if Offsetpitch is non-zero), this value is a bitmask used
to determine which channels are <b>not</b> pitch-shifted.
For example, if the value of Offsetfilter is <font face="Courier">1&lt;&lt;9</font>, then channel
10 will not be affected.  (And, in fact, 1&lt;&lt;9 is the default
value of Offsetfilter.)  Any number of bits in Offsetfilter can be set.
<listitem name="Offsetpitch" bold="yes" />
If non-zero, all scheduled MIDI output will be pitch-shifted by
the value of Offsetpitch.
<listitem name="Pathseparator" bold="yes" />
This string is the character that separates the components of <font face="Courier">Keypath</font>.
Default is ":".
<listitem name="Phraseflashnotes" bold="yes" />
If this value is non-zero, notes within phrase windows are flashed
as they are played.  Default is 1.  If your CPU is too busy, setting
this to 0 can help a bit.
<listitem name="Printsplit" bold="yes" />
When long phrase values are printed, they are broken up on separate lines
(each line terminated with a backslash),
and Printsplit is the number of characters on each line.  The default
value is 77.  To disable splitting of lines entirely, set Printsplit to 0.
<listitem name="Record" bold="yes" />
When non-zero, recording of MIDI input is enabled.  Default is 1.
<listitem name="Recorded" bold="yes" />
This phrase collects all MIDI input (when <font face="Courier">Record</font> is non-zero).
<listitem name="Recsched" bold="yes" />
When non-zero, scheduled MIDI output is included
in the <font face="Courier">Recorded</font> phrase.  Default is 0.
<listitem name="Sync" bold="yes" />
If non-zero, time is advanced from clocks on MIDI input instead
of being driven by the computer's clock.
This allows synchronization with other MIDI devices (e.g. a drum machine
or sequencer).
Default is 0.
<listitem name="Throttle" bold="yes" />
This determins how many KeyKit instructions (internal interpreted
instructions, not KeyKit statements) are executed per each
check for realtime activity.
Default value is 100.
<listitem name="Version" bold="yes" />
This string is the KeyKit version number (e.g. <font face="Courier">"6.0a"</font>).
<blankline/>
<blankline/>
<title2 name="Variables used in Graphics"/>
<blankline/>
<listitem name="Bendrange" bold="yes" />
This number controls the relative size of pitch-bend controller lines in
the Misc window.  Default is 16384.
<listitem name="Bendoffset" bold="yes" />
This number controls the vertical offset of the beginning of pitch-bend controller
lines in the Misc window.  Default is 64.
<listitem name="Checkcount" bold="yes" />
This controls the frequency of garbage collection activities.  Default is 20.
<listitem name="Colors" bold="yes" />
This is the number of colors (including black and white) available.
<listitem name="Font" bold="yes" />
This string is the name of the font to be used.  Default is machine-dependent,
and some machines may completely ignore it.
<listitem name="Graphics" bold="yes" />
This number is non-zero whenever graphics mode is enabled.
<listitem name="Menujump" bold="yes" />
If non-zero, moving the mouse into a menu's scroll bar will cause the
menu to immediately jump to that position.  Otherwise, scroll bar movement
is only relative.  Default is 0.  If you have trouble interacting with
the scroll bar, try setting this to 1.
<listitem name="Menuscrollwidth" bold="yes" />
This number controls the width of the scroll bar in scrolling
menus.  Default is 20.  If you have trouble getting on the scroll bar,
increase this value.
<listitem name="Menusize" bold="yes" />
This is the default maximum number of items in a pop-up menu.
When a menu becomes larger than this, it will display a scroll bar.
Default is 12.
<listitem name="Musicpath" bold="yes" />
This string is the list of directories in which to search for
music files.  Default is machine-dependent.
<listitem name="Showbar" bold="yes" />
The number of clicks between vertical measure bars.  Default is 4b.
<listitem name="Sweepquant" bold="yes" />
This number is used to quantize the sweeping of areas with sweep() and gridsweep().
<listitem name="Volstem" bold="yes" />
If non-zero, ``volume stems'' are displayed on notes.  Default is 0.
<listitem name="Volstemsize" bold="yes" />
This number controls the relative scale of volume stems.  Default is 4.
</list></document>
