<document name="KeyKit Library Functions" title="Library Functions" >
<list>
<blankline/>
<listitem name="addbootfunc(func)  " bold="yes" />
Adds a function to the list of functions that will be
automatically invoked when KeyKit is rebooted.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="allsusoff()  " bold="yes" />
Return a phrase containing a "sustain off" on all channels.
  Useful for resetting things if you have a hanging note.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="ano()  " bold="yes" />
Return a phrase containing all-notes-off messages on each channel.
This does not include note-offs for each individual note, however.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="apply(target,source,apptype,startquant)  " bold="yes" />
Apply stuff (pitch, volume, timing, etc.) from the source phrase
to the target phrase.  The apptype is the bitwise-or of PITCH,
VOLUME, DURATION, TIME, EXACTTIME, CHANNEL.
Default apptype is TIME|DURATION
<blankline/>
<listitem name="applyfunc(p,func,chunksize)  " bold="yes" />
This function splits a phrase into chunksize-sized chunks,
applies the function func to some of them (every other one,
by default), and returns the result, pasted back together.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="arpeggio(phrase)  " bold="yes" />
Returns an arpeggiated version of the phrase.  One way of describing
it is that all the notes have been separated and then put back
together, back-to-back.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="arrayprint(array)  " bold="yes" />
Prints all the elements in the given array.
Works for arrays of any dimension.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="arraysort  " bold="yes" />
Sorts the elements in the given array,
and returns the sorted array.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="attime(phrase,time)  " bold="yes" />
Returns those notes in the specified phrase that are
sounding at the specified time.  If a note ends exactly
at the specified time, it is not included.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="bpm(beatsperminute)  " bold="yes" />
Changes the tempo based on beats per minute,
rather than microseconds per beat
<blankline/>
<listitem name="bsdemo()  " bold="yes" />
This is an example of using the bsguide() function.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="bsguide(arr,arrkey,keyguide,noteguide,stepsize,lng)  " bold="yes" />
Synthesize a monophonic phrase based on these arguments:

arr
.br
An array whose elements are phrases, each one specifying
the allowable notes that can be used on a given step.
For example, if bsarr contained these elements:
arr[1]='c' ; arr[2]='c,e,g' ; arr[3]='c,g' ; arr[4]='g'
then only a 'c' would be allowed in the first step, and
the second step would allow a 'c', 'e', or 'g'.
The arr array can be of any size; when it runs out,
it is reused from the beginning.  For example, in the
example above, the fifth step would allow only a 'c'.

arrkey
.br
The key that the phrases in the arr array are meant
to be in.  E.g. in the example above, the value of arrkey
would most likely be 'c'.  This is needed so that
the arr array can be transposed to other keys.

keyguide
.br
A phrase that will determine the key (or really, chords)
in the final result.  For example, if the value of
keyguide was 'c,c,c,f', the notes picked during the first
three beats would be based in C, and the final beat would
be based in F.  Essentially the phrases in the arr array
are transposed based on these notes.

noteguide
.br
A phrase whose notes will be used as "guide" points in
picking the pitches in the final result.  For example,
if the guide phrase was 'co5,co4,co3', then the first note
in the final result would be as close as possible to 'co5',
and the note picked on the second beat would be as close as
possible to 'co4'.  If the notes of guide are very close
together, then they will strongly influence the general shape
of the final result.  If instead the notes of guide are
farther apart, then the final result will be allowed to meander
more freely between the guide notes (but still subject to the
contraints of the arr array described above).  E.g. a guide
phrase of 'co5d384,co4' would allow 4 beats of meandering
before being pushed back toward 'co4'.

stepsize
.br
This is the step size of the final result.  E.g. a value
of 1b/4 means the result would consist of sixteenth notes.

lng
.br
The desired length of the final result.

<blankline/>
<listitem name="canonic(note)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the canonical pitch of a note,
ie. a number between 0 and 11.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="chadjust(melody,chords)  " bold="yes" />
Adjusts the notes of the melody phrase so that they fall on the notes
of the chords that are playing (at the same time) in the chords phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="changeprogchange(p,frompatchnum,topatchnum)  " bold="yes" />
Return p, where every program change message matching
the frompatchnum is changed to topatchnum.
The program change numbers are 1-based.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="chaninfo(p)  " bold="yes" />
Return a string giving channel information about phrase p.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="chfilter(melody,chord)  " bold="yes" />
Return a copy of the melody phrase, leaving only those notes that
match the chords that occur in the chord phrase at the same time.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="chord(root,type,oct)  " bold="yes" />
Return a chord, where root is the root note, oct is the
octave number, and type is a string that identifies the
type of chord - possible values are:
"major", "minor", "maj7", "min7", "maj9", "min9", "sus", "dim", "aug", 
"Maj69", "MajB769", "HalfDim", "Dim9", 
"NModMaj1", "NModMaj2", "NModMaj3",
"NModDom1", "NModDom2", "NModDom3", "NModDom4", 
"ArtDim", "AOVoic1", "AOVoic2", "AllMaj", "Res", 
"Vitr1", "Vitr2", "Fourths", "Pr1", "Pr2", "Pr3", "Pr4"
<blankline/>
<listitem name="closest(note,scale [,direction] )  " bold="yes" />
Returns a note from the specified scale that is closest in pitch
to the specified note.  If the optional direction argument is given,
it specifies the direction (1==up, -1==down) that we want the
chosen note to be in (relative to the original note).  Specifying
the direction also guarantees that a note different from the
original is chosen (if possible).
<blankline/>
<listitem name="closestmap(nt,map)  " bold="yes" />
The map argument is a set of notes.  This function takes the
single note nt and changes its pitch to the closest note in the map set.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="closestt(phrase,time,limit)  " bold="yes" />
Return the single note in the specified phrase that is closest
in time to the specified time.  If the limit argument is given,
the search is limited to notes within that amount of time
(i.e. to notes between (time-limit) and (time+limit)).
<blankline/>
<listitem name="completescale(key,scalename)  " bold="yes" />
Return a phrase which is in the given key and scale, and extends
from the lowest note (in the key/scale) to the highest note.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="completescalephrase(p)  " bold="yes" />
Return a phrase which has the notes in p duplicated across all octaves.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="consloop()  " bold="yes" />
This is intended to be the one-and-only task that reads from
the Consinfifo, a special fifo that is automatically opened
whenever KeyKit is booted, and to which KeyKit sends any characters
typed on the console.  consloop() forwards the characters to whatever
task is supposed to be reading the console.  If Consgrabfifo is
set, it will send them there, otherwise it sends them to the
main command interpreter, which is reading from interpfifo.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="constant()  " bold="yes" />
This function initializes various constants that
are needed by other funcitons.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="controller(ch,cn,val)  " bold="yes" />
Return a controller message, where ch is the channel (1-based),
cn is the controller number, and val is the value.
Removes all bank-select controller messages (controller 0
followed by controller 32) from a phrase.
Note that it leaves the program change message
which usually follows.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="dedup(ph)  " bold="yes" />
Remove any duplicate notes (in time and pitch) from a phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="dedupdur(ph)  " bold="yes" />
Remove any duplicate notes (including comparison of duration)
from a phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="delay(ph,tm)  " bold="yes" />
Return phrase ph, delayed by time tm.
Removes all rests (sections where nothing is playing)
from a phrase.
Set up input/output ports.  Look for a file keylocal.k first,
and if that doesn't exist, use some defaults
<blankline/>
<listitem name="dupsof(p)  " bold="yes" />
Return a phrase containing one copy of any notes that
are duplicated in phrase p
<blankline/>
<listitem name="echo(ph,num,rtime,rfactor)  " bold="yes" />
Return phrase ph echoed num times, with rtime delay between
each echo, and with the volume of each echo decreased by rfactor.
NEW BEHAVIOUR - 8/9/99 - the length of the result is
now explicitly set.  This is more "right", but some algorithms
may have been depending (unknowingly) on the old semantic.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="echomaster(ph,fnum,ftime,ffactor,bnum,btime,bfactor)  " bold="yes" />
Return phrase ph with echoes, forward and back.
fnum is the number of forward echos, ftime is the echo time, ffactor
is the volume reduction factor.  bnum/btime/bfactor is for the
backward echos.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="evalstring(s)  " bold="yes" />
Takes a string and evals it.  Useful when you want to
put something in the background - you just "task evalstring(...)"
<blankline/>
<listitem name="eventime(ph)  " bold="yes" />
Return phrase ph with all of its notes evenly spaced in time.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="filetopitches(filename)  " bold="yes" />
<blankline/>
<listitem name="findroot(ph)  " bold="yes" />
Given a phrase, try to guess the root of what's being played.
The algorithm was given to me by Christopher John Rolfe (rolfe@sfu.ca),
who says it was culled from W.Russo, Jazz Composition and Orchestration,
p.25, ex.7.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="findtask(function_name)  " bold="yes" />
This function looks for a running task that is executing
the named function (which is specified as a string, not as
a function value).  If found, the task id is returned.
If not found, the return value is -1.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="flip(phrase [,about])  " bold="yes" />
Flip the pitches of the specified phrase about some intermediate
pitch (i.e. high notes become lower, and low notes become higher).
Given a single argument, the flip is done about the average pitch
of the original phrase.  A second argument can specify a particular
pitch about which to flip.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="floor(f)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the floor (maximum integer that is less than f).
<blankline/>
<listitem name="fractal(ph,depth)  " bold="yes" />
Returns phrase ph fractalized - each note becomes a miniature
version of the entire phrase, transposed by the note's pitch.
The depth determines how many times this process is repeated.
Watch out, this will produce huge phrases.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="gcd(n1,...)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the greatest common divisor of all of its arguments
<blankline/>
<listitem name="gcd2(n1,n2)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the greatest common divisor of two integers
<blankline/>
<listitem name="getsysexdump(sendmessage,tmout)  " bold="yes" />
This function retrieves a sysex dump from an attached MIDI device.
The 'sendmessage' argument is expected to be a sysex message that,
when sent to the device, will cause it to send back a sysex dump
(or any sysex message, really).  For example, for a TX81Z, the
value of 'xf0432004f7' will cause it to send back a sysex dump
containing all patches.  The 'tmout' parameter is a timeout value
in milliseconds - if this time elapses without receiving any output
from MIDI input, the function will abort and return an empty phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="gmresetall()  " bold="yes" />
Returns a phrase containing controller messages that reset
everything appropriately for the beginning of
a General MIDI piece.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="grabmouse()  " bold="yes" />
This function arranges for all mouse messages to be intercepted and
sent to a particular window, rather than being routed to the windows
underneath the mouse.  When you want to restore things to normal,
call ungrabmouse().
<blankline/>
<listitem name="grabmousefifo()  " bold="yes" />
This function arranges for all mouse messages to be intercepted and
sent to a new fifo, rather than being routed to the windows underneath
the mouse.  The fifo id of this new fifo is returned as the value
of grabmousefifo().  When you want to restore things to normal,
call ungrabmousefifo().
<blankline/>
<listitem name="gridinit()  " bold="yes" />
This is the code that initializes the graphics mode of KeyKit.
It starts up things like the mouseloop() task, which handles
mouse input, and sets up the screen with the initial tool set
by calling toolrc().
<blankline/>
<listitem name="highest(phrase)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the highest-pitched note in the specified phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="highestnt(phrase)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the highest-pitched note in the specified phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="inport(port)  " bold="yes" />
Open a MIDI input port
<blankline/>
<listitem name="interploop()  " bold="yes" />
This is the main command interpreter that executes the statements
that a user types interactively on the console.  It reads from
the interpfifo fifo, and characters are normally put on this fifo
by consloop().
<blankline/>
<listitem name="isinscale(note,scale)  " bold="yes" />
Return true (non-zero) if the specified note exists in the
specified scale.  The scale phrase need only specify a give pitch
once - it is assumed to be duplicated over all octaves.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="isnearbeat(note ,beat_interval, tolerance )  " bold="yes" />
<blankline/>
<listitem name="isonbeat(note [,beat_interval] )  " bold="yes" />
Returns true (non-zero) if the given note lands on the beat.
The default beat interval is 1b; a second argument can specify an
different interval (e.g. isonbeat(note,4b) would return
true if the note fell on any 4-beat mark).
<blankline/>
<listitem name="keyrc()  " bold="yes" />
This is the very first function called by KeyKit,
unless the -r option is specified when KeyKit is invoked.
This function must initialize everything necessary
for the proper running of KeyKit.  This is normally done
by calling normboot() to set up the command interpreter and
start other primary tasks.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="khslider(vmin,vmax,vinit,invokefunc,args)  " bold="yes" />
Create a horizontal slider object and return its id.  When slider is
moved, the invokefunc will be called with 2 arguments - the first
will be the current value of the slider, and the second will be the
args value.  The vmin, vmax, and vinit values are the minimum,
maximum, and initial values for the slider.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="kslider(vmin,vmax,vinit,invokefunc,args)  " bold="yes" />
Create a slider object and return its id.  When the slider is
moved, the invokefunc will be called with 2 arguments - the first
will be the current value of the slider, and the second will be the
args value.  The vmin, vmax, and vinit values are the minimum,
maximum, and initial values for the slider.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="kvalbutton(vals)  " bold="yes" />
<blankline/>
<listitem name="lastbunch(ph,spc,types)  " bold="yes" />
Return the last "bunch" of notes in ph.  The value of spc is the time
that determines where the bunch ends - as soon as a blank space of
that size is detected, the bunch has ended.  This is useful for
grabbing the last little bit of the Recorded phrase.
If a third argument is given, it is a bitmask of note types
to look for - all other types are ignored.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="latest(phrase)  " bold="yes" />
Return the ending time of the latest note in the given phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="legato(phrase)  " bold="yes" />
Extends the duration of each note to abutt the start of the next note.
Doesn't modify the duration of the last note.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="limitval(v,minv,maxv)  " bold="yes" />
Takes a number and limits it to the specified range.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="listports()  " bold="yes" />
A simple utility that lists the available MIDI ports to the console.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="lowest(phrase)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the lowest pitch in the specified phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="lowestnt(phrase)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the lowest-pitched note in the specified phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="makenote(pitch [,duration [,volume [,chan]]] )  " bold="yes" />
A simple utility for generating a single-note phrase.
The pitch is the only required argument; additional
arguments specify the duration, velocity, and channel.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="makerootevery(melody,intrvl)  " bold="yes" />
Figure out a root note (using findroot()) every intrvl beats,
and return it.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="maxvolume(phrase)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the largest volume in the specified phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="midiloop()  " bold="yes" />
This is intended to be the one-and-only task which reads messages
from the Midiinfifo, a special fifo that is opened whenever KeyKit
is rebooted, and to which KeyKit sends messages containing
all MIDI input.  Any task wanting to read MIDI input should add
an entry to the Midiin array.  The index of the Midiin array
is normally the task id, and the value of the array element
is the fifo id.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="milliclicks(milli)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the number of clicks equivalent to the specified
number of milliseconds.  Note that this is dependent upon
the current tempo().
<blankline/>
<listitem name="millisince(tm)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the number of milliseconds since a given time
<blankline/>
<listitem name="millisleep(milli)  " bold="yes" />
Sleep (i.e. pause the task which calls this function)
for the specified number of milliseconds.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="minduration(phrase)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the smallest duration in the specified phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="minvolume(phrase)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the lowest volume in the specified phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="mono(phrase,type)  " bold="yes" />
Returns a monophonic version of the specified phrase.
If type==0, high notes are given priority (e.g. if two notes are
playing simultaneously, the higher note will be chosen).
If type==1, low notes are given priority.  If type==2,
the priority is randomized.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="mouseloop()  " bold="yes" />
This task is intended to be the one-and-only task that reads
directly from the Mousefifo, a special fifo that is opened
whenever KeyKit is rebooted, and to which KeyKit sends messages
about changes in the mouse state.  mouseloop() normally figures
out which window is underneath the mouse, and sends the message
to the Mousein fifo for that window.  If someone wants to grab the
mouse, they should set Mousegrabwind, and mouseloop() will instead
send the mouse messages to that window.  This procedure should be done
with the grabmouse() and ungrabmouse() functions.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="nanopatch(ch,bank,prog)  " bold="yes" />
Return sysex that changes a parts bank/program.
Assumes that the 16 parts are assigned to channels 1-16.
ch is 1-based
bank is 0-based
prog is 0-based
<blankline/>
<listitem name="nextquant(number,quantize)  " bold="yes" />
This function quantizes the specified number using the specified
quantize value, and returns the result.  The result is guaranteed to
be greater than the original number; if quantization would produce
a smaller number, it is increased by the quantize value.  This is
typically used when you want to quantize a time value, and want to
guarantee that the result will refer to some time in the future,
not in the past.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="nexttime(ph,st)  " bold="yes" />
Return the time of the next note AFTER time 'st', in phrase 'ph'
If there are no notes after it, returns -1;
<blankline/>
<listitem name="nonnotes(ph)  " bold="yes" />
Return all non-notes (i.e. controller, sysex, etc) of ph.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="normboot()  " bold="yes" />
This is intended to be the default function that gets called
when KeyKit initially boots or reboots.  KeyKit calls
Rebootfunc() when it reboots, so in order for this function
to be used, the statement "Rebootfunc=normboot" should be
included in keyrc().  Any tasks that must always be
active (for example, the loops that monitor mouse and
console input) should be started here.  To register a
function that will be automatically restarted upon a reboot, 
you should add it to the Rebootfuncs array.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="normexit()  " bold="yes" />
<blankline/>
<listitem name="normintr()  " bold="yes" />
This function is intended to be the default value of Intrfunc,
which KeyKit calls when an interrupt is received, typically
when the user presses the interrupt character on the console.
This function forces a reboot.  If graphics mode is enabled,
an attempt is made to save the current tool configuration
in the file "keydump.lst", which will then be restored after
the reboot.  In this way, a fairly clean restart is performed.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="normredraw()  " bold="yes" />
This function is intended to be the default value of Redrawfunc,
which KeyKit calls whenever the screen must be redrawn.
It redraws the root window (i.e. erasing the screen), and
then sends a redraw message to all children windows (i.e. all
the active tools).
<blankline/>
<listitem name="normresize()  " bold="yes" />
This function is intended to be the default value of Resizefunc,
which KeyKit calls whenever the screen is resized.  Normally
this function does nothing.  By setting the variable Autoresize
to 1 (e.g. in liblocal/prerc.k), you can cause this function to
automatically resize all the active tools to fit within the new
screen size.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="nrpn(ch,mm,ll)  " bold="yes" />
Return an NRPN message constructed from ch (channel, 1-based),
mm (most-significant byte) and ll (least-significant byte).
<blankline/>
<listitem name="nsimul(ph)  " bold="yes" />
Return the maximum number of simultaneously-sounding notes in a phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="numquant(number,quantize)  " bold="yes" />
This function quantizes the specified number using the specified
quantize value, and returns the result.  The result may be less
than the original number.  If you want to guarantee that the
result is not less than the original (which is typical when you are
quantizing a time value and want to guarantee that the result is
some time in the future), use nextquant().
<blankline/>
<listitem name="onlynotes(ph)  " bold="yes" />
Return only the regular notes (non-controller, non-sysex, etc) of ph.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="ornament(ph,orn,doscaleng)  " bold="yes" />
Apply phrase orn to each note of phrase ph - i.e. each note of
phrase ph will be turned into a copy of phrase orn.
If doscaleng is non-zero, then the copy will be scaled to the
duration of the notes in phrase orn.  If doscaleng is zero,
the copy will have the original timing.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="outport(port)  " bold="yes" />
Opena a MIDI output port
<blankline/>
<listitem name="patchunmap_sc8850(p)  " bold="yes" />
If p is a patch change message, return its entry in the patchmap
Return 0 if it's not a patch message.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="patchunmap_sd80(p)  " bold="yes" />
If p is a patch change message, return its entry in the patchmap
Return 0 if it's not a patch message.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="pathescape(s)  " bold="yes" />
Takes a file pathname, and returns a version of
the string that can be safely printed to a file and re-read.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="picknote(phrase, n)  " bold="yes" />
Returns n random notes from the specified phrase.  If n is omitted,
a single random note is returned.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="pickphr(phrase1,phrase2,phrase3...)  " bold="yes" />
Randomly chooses and returns one of its argument phrases.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="pitchbend(ch,val)  " bold="yes" />
 Construct a pitchbend message, where ch is the channel (1-based)
 and val is the pitchbend value, input range is -8192 to 8191.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="pitchlimit(p,p1,p2)  " bold="yes" />
Adjust the pitches of notes in phrase p so that they
fall between p1 and p2, by shifting the notes in octave increments.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="preecho(ph,num,rtime,factor)  " bold="yes" />
Return phrase ph with each note preceeded by 'pre' echoes.
num is the number of echoes, rtime is the time between them,
and rfactor is the volume factor (between 0.0 and 1.0)
If not provided, rtime and rfactor default to 1b and 0.9
<blankline/>
<listitem name="prelocaldefaults()  " bold="yes" />
This sets any default values before keylocal.k is called.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="prevquant(number,quantize)  " bold="yes" />
This function quantizes the specified number using the specified
quantize value, and returns a result that is equal to or less than
the original number.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="progchange(patchnum,ch)  " bold="yes" />
Return a program change message, where patchnum is the
patch number (1-based), and ch is the channel (1-based).
<blankline/>
<listitem name="quantize(phrase,quant [,limit] )  " bold="yes" />
Quantize a phrase.  Each note's starting time will be
quantized by the specified quant value.  If a limit
is specified, notes that would need to be moved by an
amount larger than this limit will not be adjusted at all.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="quantizedur(ph,qnt)  " bold="yes" />
Quantize the duration of all notes in ph.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="quantizefirst(ph,qnt)  " bold="yes" />
Quantize the first note of ph, and shift the
rest of the phrase by the same amount.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="randdur(phrase,range)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the phrase with the duration of its notes randomly
varied within the specified range.  For example, if the
range value is 2, the note durations will be adjusted by
values ranging from +2 to -2.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="randpitch(phrase,range)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the phrase with the pitch of its notes randomly
varied within the specified range.  For example, if the
range value is 2, the note pitches will be adjusted by
values ranging from +2 to -2.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="randvol(phrase,range)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the phrase with the velocity of its notes randomly
varied within the specified range.  For example, if the
range value is 2, the note velocities will be adjusted by
values ranging from +2 to -2.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="rcdefaults()  " bold="yes" />
This sets any default values for which it is intended that
they can be overridden by postrc().
Machine-dependent rcdefault things
<blankline/>
<listitem name="readedit(fifo,prompt [,history] )  " bold="yes" />
This function reads from a fifo, allowing line editing.
When a complete line has been entered, it is returned.
The optional third argument lets you access and maintain
a history of previous lines (this feature is not yet implemented).
<blankline/>
<listitem name="readedit2(fifo,prompt)  " bold="yes" />
This is a variation of readedit that allows you to press ESC
and get put into "notepad" on the history.  To activate,
set ConsoleReadedit=readedit2 in your liblocal/postrc.k
When you're done writing your script in the text editor, save the file,
close the editor (optional), then press ESC again. The whole KeyKit code
you edited will be evaluated as a single line (so take care to end your 
  lines with a ";")

  Another feature of readedit2 is the TAB key which recalls previous
<blankline/>
<listitem name="readfile(filename)  " bold="yes" />
This function reads an entire file (all lines of it)
and returns it as a single string.
  NOTE: might or might not read the newlines at the end of lines
  Currently it gets rid of the newlines, but that's not good.
  I'm reluctant to change it without checking whether it breaks something.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="readkey(filename)  " bold="yes" />
This function reads a phrase from the specified file, which is
is expected to contain a phrase in KeyKit format, i.e. the
same as a phrase constant in the KeyKit language.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="readmf(filename)  " bold="yes" />
Reads the specified Standard MIDI File and returns its
contents as a single phrase (with all tracks merged).
<blankline/>
<listitem name="readraw(filename)  " bold="yes" />
<blankline/>
<listitem name="repeat(phrase,num_times)  " bold="yes" />
Repeat a phrase as many times as specified.  The length attribute
of the phrase determines the offset of the repetitions.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="repfade(p,ntimes,inout)  " bold="yes" />
Repeat the phrase the specified number of times, gradually fading it
in or out (by including or excluding more notes on each repeat).
If inout>0, it starts out including only a couple of notes, and ends by
including the entire phrase - ie. a fade in.  If inout is less than 0,
it's a fade out.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="repleng(phrase,length)  " bold="yes" />
Repeat the specified phrase as many times as it takes
to fill the specified length of time.  The resultant
phrase is truncated to the exact length, if it doesn't
come out evenly.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="resetall()  " bold="yes" />
Returns a phrase containing controller messages that reset
pitch bend, modulation, breath control, sustain, and channel pressure
on all 16 channels to nominal values (i.e. 0, or in the case
of pitch bend, 0x40).
<blankline/>
<listitem name="reverse(ph)  " bold="yes" />
Reverse the phrase in time, so the first notes come last,
and the last notes come first.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="revpitch(phrase)  " bold="yes" />
Reverse the pitches of a phrase (e.g. the pitch of the first note
will become the pitch of the last note).  The timing is left intact.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="round(f)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the rounded integer value of f.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="sc8850patch(channel,patchnum,variation)  " bold="yes" />
Return the message that will set an sc8850/sc8820/scd-70 patch
channel and patchnum are 1-based, variation is 0-based (to match
<blankline/>
<listitem name="scadjust(melody,scale)  " bold="yes" />
Adjust the notes in the melody phrase so that each note falls on
the closest note in the scale phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="scadur(phrase,factor)  " bold="yes" />
Scale the durations of a phrase by multiplying the duration of
each note by a specified factor.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="scafilt(melody,scale)  " bold="yes" />
Return a copy of the melody phrase, leaving only those notes
that fall on the scale specified by the scale phrase.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="scaleng(phrase,length)  " bold="yes" />
Scale the phrase to the specified length by expanding it length-wise,
adjusting both the time and duration of the notes.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="scatimes(phrase,factor)  " bold="yes" />
Scale a phrase by multiplying the time and duration of
each note by a specified factor.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="scavol(phrase,factor)  " bold="yes" />
Scale the volume of a phrase by multiplying the volume of
each note by a specified factor.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="sd80patch(channel,patchnum,variation)  " bold="yes" />
Return the message that will set an sd80/sc8820/scd-70 patch
channel is 1-based, patchnum is 0-based (because the sd80
patch list used 0-based), and variation is 0-based (to match
the LCD display of the sd80.
The soundset value is
	80 (special 1)
	81 (special 2)
	96 (classical)
	97 (contemporary)
	98 (solo)
	99 (enhanced)
	87 (user)
<blankline/>
<listitem name="seconds(secs)  " bold="yes" />
Returns the number of clicks in a given number of seconds.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="setdefaults()  " bold="yes" />
This function sets various global default values.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="shuffle(ph)  " bold="yes" />
This function takes a phrase, splits in in 2 halves (along time)
and shuffles the result (ie. first a note from the first half, then
a note from the second half, etc.).  The timing of the original
phrase is applied to the result.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="spread(ph,num,rtime,rfactor)  " bold="yes" />
Return phrase ph "spread" num times, with rtime delay between
each iteration, and with the volume of each iteration decreased
by rfactor.  A "spread" is like an echo, except that notes are
repeated in BOTH directions, forward and back.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="status([str])  " bold="yes" />
When called with no arguments, this function prints a list of all
currently-running tasks.  If a string argument is given, the list
will only contain those tasks whose stacktrace (the output of
taskinfo(tid,"trace")) contains that string.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="step(ph,stepdur)  " bold="yes" />
Convert a phrase to be in step time, ie. all notes with the same
spacing and duration.  Overlapped notes (no matter how small the
overlap) are played at the same time.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="strip(ph)  " bold="yes" />
Strip off any leading and trailing rests from a phrase
<blankline/>
<listitem name="sussect(time,channel)  " bold="yes" />
Generate a phrase with controller messages that press the sustain
pedal on the specified channel and let it up after the specified
amount of time.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="swapnote(ph)  " bold="yes" />
Swap every two notes in the phrase ph.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="syncphr(phrase)  " bold="yes" />
This function returns a copy of the specified phrase, shifting
the starting time so that it is as close as possible to 0 (but not
less than 0).  The amount by which the time is shifted must be a
multiple of lng (which, if not specified, is the length of the Met.
This is typically used when you want to play a phrase that has
been taken from the middle of some other phrase.  The goal is
that the playback should still be synchronized to the current Met.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="tonerow(p)  " bold="yes" />
Better version of tonerow, works on all types of notes.
Return a tone row of the notes in phrase p.
Each note in the original phrase appears exactly
once in the result, but in a random position.
The original time/duration of the notes is retained.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="tonerow_old(p)  " bold="yes" />
Return a tone row of the notes in phrase p.
Each note in the original phrase appears exactly
once in the result, but in a random position.
The original time/duration of the notes is retained.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="transpose(phrase,amount)  " bold="yes" />
Transposes the phrase by the specified amount.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="trrackpatch(ch,bank,prog)  " bold="yes" />
Return sysex that changes a parts bank/program.
Assumes that the 16 parts are assigned to channels 1-16.
ch is 1-based
bank is 0-based
prog is 0-based
<blankline/>
<listitem name="ungrabmouse(w)  " bold="yes" />
This is the complement to grabmouse(), releasing the mouse so that
mouse events are distributed normally.  The w (window) argument
should be the same as that passed to grabmouse().
<blankline/>
<listitem name="ungrabmousefifo(fifo)  " bold="yes" />
This is the complement to grabmouse(), releasing the mouse so that
mouse events are distributed normally.  The fifo argument should be
the fifo that was created and returned by grabmouse().
<blankline/>
<listitem name="uniqnum()  " bold="yes" />
This function returns a new unique number.  Useful for inventing
id numbers for menus, or for any other purpose.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="virusbpatch(part,bank,prog)  " bold="yes" />
Return sysex that changes a parts bank/program.
Assumes that the 16 parts are assigned to channels 1-16.
ch is 1-based
bank is 1-based
prog is 0-based
<blankline/>
<listitem name="virusbunpatch(p)  " bold="yes" />
If p is a patch change message, return its name.
Return "" if it's not a patch message.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="warrange(args)  " bold="yes" />
This is used to let you interactively rearrange windows.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="wconsole(window)  " bold="yes" />
This tool is a console window, allowing interaction with
the interactive command interpreter.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="wdelete()  " bold="yes" />
This utility lets you point to and delete an object.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="wgroup()  " bold="yes" />
Create a phrase group for multi-track editing.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="wpack(args)  " bold="yes" />
This is used to let you interactively pack windows.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="wsmmgroup()  " bold="yes" />
Create a phrase group for multi-track editing.
<blankline/>
<listitem name="xystr(xyarray)  " bold="yes" />
This function is used when you want to print(the value of an xyarray.
It returns a string version of the specified xyarray.
For example, xystr(xy(0,0,4,4)) would equal "0,0,4,4".
It works for 2-element xyarrays (i.e. with subscripts "x" and "y")
as well as 4-element xyarrays ("x0", "y0", "x1", "y1").
</list>
</document>
